<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>William Okech</title>
<link>https://williamokech.netlify.app/series_2.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://williamokech.netlify.app/series_2.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>This is William Okech&#39;s personal Blog.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.269</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 21:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A roof over your head</title>
  <dc:creator>William Okech</dc:creator>
  <link>https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_2/post_2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="introduction" class="level1">
<h1>Introduction</h1>
<p>An aerial view of most settlements in Kenya will demonstrate that many residential home roofs are constructed using iron sheets.</p>
<p>Indeed, this is confirmed by the Kenya Population and Housing Census (2019) report <sup>1</sup> <sup>2</sup> where we see that 4 out of every 5 households (total number = 12,043,016) in Kenya is roofed using iron sheets (Figure 1). Overall, the top 5 building materials are iron sheets (80.3%), concrete (8.2%), grass/twigs (5.1%), makuti (sun-dried coconut palm leaves; 1.6%), and asbestos (1.4%). Despite the widespread use of iron sheets, it is surprising to note that 1.4% (2.2% urban and 0.9% rural) of residential household roofs (which is approximately 170,000) are covered with asbestos-based roofing materials (NB: this figure does not include public buildings such as educational institutions and government facilities).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_2/images/national_treemap.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Figure 1: Roof types in Kenya (visualizations generated in RStudio)</p>
</section>
<section id="asbestos-and-its-potential-risks" class="level1">
<h1>Asbestos and its potential risks</h1>
<p>Asbestos refers to a class of six minerals that naturally form a bundle of fibers. These fibers have many properties that make them attractive, including a lack of electrical conductivity, and chemical, heat, and fire resistance. Historically, asbestos has been used for various commercial and industrial applications, including roofing shingles, automobile brakes, and textured paints for walls and ceilings <sup>3</sup>. However, using asbestos for products that come into regular contact with humans is quite problematic. Why? Asbestos is a known human carcinogen, and the primary risk factor for most mesotheliomas is asbestos exposure <sup>4</sup> <sup>5</sup>. Furthermore, asbestos exposure (depending on the frequency, amount, and type) can cause asbestosis, pleural disease, and cancer. If asbestos-based materials remain intact, there is minimal risk to the user, but if materials are damaged via natural degradation or during home demolition and remodeling, tiny asbestos fibers will be released into the air <sup>6</sup> <sup>7</sup>. In Kenya, Legal Notice No.&nbsp;121 of the Environmental Management and Coordination (Waste Management) Regulations (2006)<sup>8</sup> states that waste containing asbestos is classified as hazardous. Why should Kenyans be concerned about this? In the 2013/2014 financial year, Kenya spent approximately one-tenth of its total health budget on asbestos-related cancers <sup>9</sup> <sup>10</sup> <sup>11</sup>.</p>
<p>Where do we find high numbers of asbestos-based roofs in Kenya? As previously stated, 1.4% of households in Kenya have asbestos-based roofs. Figure 2 demonstrates the percentage of households with asbestos-based roofs in every county in Kenya. Interestingly, 4 (Nairobi, Kajiado, Machakos, and Kiambu) out of the top 6 counties (from a total of 47) fall within the Nairobi Metropolitan region.</p>
</section>
<section id="where-do-we-find-high-numbers-of-asbestos-based-roofs-in-kenya" class="level1">
<h1>Where do we find high numbers of asbestos-based roofs in Kenya?</h1>
<p>As previously stated, 1.4% of households in Kenya have asbestos-based roofs. Figure 2 demonstrates the percentage of households with asbestos-based roofs in every county in Kenya. Interestingly, 4 (Nairobi, Kajiado, Machakos, and Kiambu) out of the top 6 counties (from a total of 47) fall within the Nairobi Metropolitan region.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_2/images/all_counties_asbestos_barplot_map.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Figure 2: Percentage(%) of households with asbestos-based roofs distributed by county (visualizations generated using RStudio)</p>
<p>Next, I investigated the subcounties with the highest number of households with asbestos-based roofs. The top 5 subcounties are located within Nairobi county, with Embakasi subcounty taking the lead with just over 8,000 households.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_2/images/top_households_asbestos_raw.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Figure 3: The top ten subcounties with the highest number of households that have asbestos-based roofs (visualizations generated using RStudio)</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level1">
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p>Overall, this study demonstrates that a notable proportion of Kenyan households used asbestos-based roofing materials, with Nairobi Metropolitan county accounting for the largest number of households. It is widely acknowledged that asbestos is harmful to our health, and asbestos-related diseases impose a significant burden on the economy. However, the impact of these roofs on the health of residents may not be fully apparent as asbestos exposure may also occur in various settings such as educational facilities and government institutions. To lessen the impact of asbestos exposure, it would be beneficial for local/county governments to educate residents about the dangers of asbestos and facilitate the complex and costly removal of asbestos-based roofing materials.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Kenya National Bureau of Statistics. The 2019 Kenya Population and Housing Census. Volume I: Population by County and Sub-County and Volume III: Distribution of Population by Age and Sex.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Shelmith Kariuki (2020). rKenyaCensus: 2019 Kenya Population and Housing Census Results. R package version 0.0.2.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Learn About Asbestos (no date) EPA. Environmental Protection Agency. Available at: https://www.epa.gov/asbestos/learn-about-asbestos (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Asbestos exposure and cancer risk fact sheet (no date) National Cancer Institute. Available at: https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/risk/substances/asbestos/asbestos-fact-sheet (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Asbestos (no date) World Health Organization. World Health Organization. Available at: https://www.iarc.who.int/risk-factor/asbestos/ (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Learn About Asbestos (no date) EPA. Environmental Protection Agency. Available at: https://www.epa.gov/asbestos/learn-about-asbestos (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Asbestos and your health (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Available at: https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/asbestos/index.html (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Act Title: ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT AND CO-ORDINATION (no date) No.&nbsp;8 of 1999. Available at: http://kenyalaw.org:8181/exist/kenyalex/sublegview.xql?subleg=No.+8+of+1999 (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>Okoth, D. (2013) Slow transition from use of asbestos raises concern as cancer cases rise, The Standard. Available at: https://www.standardmedia.co.ke/lifestyle/article/2000096118/slow-transition-from-use-of-asbestos-raises-concern-as-cancer-cases-rise (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>GCR, S. (2016) Kenya faces cancer epidemic caused by asbestos roofs, Global Construction Review. Available at: https://www.globalconstructionreview.com/kenya-faces-cancer-epid7emic-caus7ed-asbe7stos/ (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>Irungu, S. (2020) Exposure to the noxious asbestos needs to be alleviated with a lot of care, Kenya Climate Innovation Center (KCIC). Available at: https://www.kenyacic.org/2019/11/exposure-to-the-noxious-asbestos-needs-to-be-alleviated-with-a-lot-of-care/ (Accessed: December 1, 2022).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>RStudio</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>Data Stories</category>
  <category>Blog</category>
  <category>Kenya Census</category>
  <guid>https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_2/post_2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_2/images/national_treemap.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Are there more men than women in Kenya?</title>
  <dc:creator>William Okech</dc:creator>
  <link>https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/post_1.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>To answer this question, I reviewed the Kenya Population and Housing Census (2019)<sup>1</sup><sup>2</sup> report, which provides data on population by sex and age at the county and sub-county levels. This analysis was inspired by Rose Mintzer-Sweeney’s article “Sex and the Census,” published on the Datawrapper website <sup>3</sup>.</p>
<p>Various biological, cultural, public health, and economic factors can influence the global human sex ratio. For instance, at birth, the human sex ratio is “male-biased,” with approximately 105 males born per 100 girls. However, with increasing age, the susceptibility to infectious diseases, sex-selective abortions, and higher life expectancies for women can cause fluctuations in the human sex ratio<sup>4</sup>. The total Kenyan population in 2019 (according to the census) was 47,564,296. When I compared the number of males to females at the national level (Figure 1), I found that there were 98 males for every 100 females in the country<sup>5</sup>.</p>
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/images/national_sex_ratio.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Knowing there were more females than males, I sought to determine whether these differences persisted across all age groups (Figure 2).</p>
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/images/age_sex_ratio.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As expected, I observed a higher number of males compared with females between 0 to 18 years. One reason could be the higher male-to-female ratio seen at birth globally<sup>6</sup>. Between the ages of 19 to 34 years, the male-to-female ratio decreases rapidly, while from 35 to 56 years, the ratio increases rapidly. The cause of this fluctuation is not apparent, but various public health factors may be responsible for the shifts observed within these age groups. Finally, the number of males compared with females steadily decreases after age 60. One reason for this could be the prevalence of medical conditions that disproportionately affect men. Additionally, the decrease in the number of males to females could result from increases in life expectancy favoring women, as demonstrated by the Economic Survey 2022, which shows that the male life expectancy is 60.6 vs.&nbsp;66.5 for females<sup>7</sup>.</p>
<p>By focusing on the national human sex ratio, we may assume that the male-to-female ratio across all the regions in Kenya is equal. Kenya has 47 diverse counties with different population densities, climatic conditions, economic opportunities, and levels of development. Not surprisingly, we find (Figure 3) that there is a wide range of human sex ratios (90–120 males per 100 females) across the different counties (administrative units).</p>
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/images/barplot_map.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The highest sex ratio is found in Garissa county (120 males per 100 females), and the lowest is observed in Siaya county (90 males per 100 females). Many counties with low sex ratios (more females) are primarily located in the west of Kenya, and counties with high sex ratios (more males) are found in the north of Kenya. According to the Economic Survey (2022) [^8], male life expectancy in the west of Kenya is the lowest in the country. Homa Bay and Migori recorded a life expectancy of 50.5 years, which was approximately 10 years lower than that of females in the respective counties. This is against a difference of 3 to 5 years lower for males in some of the counties in the north of Kenya.</p>
<p>Within each of Kenya’s 47 counties are smaller administrative units known as sub-counties. For the final analysis, I thought it would be interesting to see whether the patterns observed at the county level were consistent across the various sub-counties.</p>
<p><img src="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/images/top_bottom_plot.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Having just observed that counties in the north of Kenya had the highest number of males per 100 females, I was surprised to find that Mandera Central (Mandera County) and Tarbaj (Wajir County) sub-counties in the north were among the sub-counties with the lowest number of males per 100 females (Figure 4). Why females tend to concentrate within specific regions in these two counties may be an interesting aspect to investigate in future studies.</p>
<p>Overall, many factors may affect the human sex ratio at the county and sub-county levels and cause the differences in the human sex ratio seen with age. High rural-urban migration, public health factors (including the prevalence of various communicable and non-communicable diseases), climate, and location’s primary source of employment may skew the number of males to females in certain sub-counties. Therefore, future investigations should focus on the causes of these variations in the human sex ratio and the implications for administrative planning at the national, county, and sub-county levels.</p>
<section id="section" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="section"></h2>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Kenya National Bureau of Statistics. The 2019 Kenya Population and Housing Census. Volume I: Population by County and Sub-County and Volume III: Distribution of Population by Age and Sex.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Shelmith Kariuki (2020). rKenyaCensus: 2019 Kenya Population and Housing Census Results. R package version 0.0.2.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Rose Mintzer-Sweeney’s article: https://blog.datawrapper.de/gender-ratio-american-history/↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Hannah Ritchie and Max Roser (2019) - “Gender Ratio.” Published online at OurWorldInData.org. Retrieved from: ‘https://ourworldindata.org/gender-ratio’ [Online Resource]↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Additionally, there were also 1,524 individuals classified as intersex, but their low numbers prevented their inclusion in the analysis.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Hannah Ritchie and Max Roser (2019) - “Gender Ratio.” Published online at OurWorldInData.org. Retrieved from: ‘https://ourworldindata.org/gender-ratio’ [Online Resource]↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Kenya National Bureau of Statistics. The Economic Survey 2022↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>RStudio</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>Data Stories</category>
  <category>Blog</category>
  <category>Kenya Census</category>
  <guid>https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/post_1.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://williamokech.netlify.app/posts/series_2/new_post_1/male-female-ratio.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="133" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
